A Guide to the Records of Eastern State Hospital, 1770-2009
Library of Virginia
- Series IV. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1791-1997., Extent: 9.125 cu. ft., 3 volumes. (Box 13-33., Volume 037-039.)
  - Subseries D. Correspondence, Subject Files and Ledgers (Superintendent), 1791-1937., Extent: 3.5 cu. ft., 3 volumes. (Box 25-33., Volume 037-039.)
    - Subject Files
      - "Periodicity of disease and bodily functions" (fragment), undated. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - "Perseverando" (poem), undated. (Box 32, Folder 3)
      - Physicians and hospitals, Lists of, 1844-1846; undated. (Box 32, Folder 4)
      - Poems (untitled), undated. (Box 32, Folder 5)
      - Porticoes, Specifications for, undated. (Box 32, Folder 6)
      - Power of attorney, (Anthony Robinson, Jr.), 1836. (Box 32, Folder 7)
      - Probable receptions, Notes on, 1844. (Box 32, Folder 8)
      - Promissary notes, 1869. (Box 32, Folder 9)
      - Quarterly report (fragment), undated. (Box 32, Folder 10)
      - Quarterly report respecting patients paying board, 1859. (Box 32, Folder 11)
      - Quartermaster's account (for Capt. D. Lambert), 1861. (Box 32, Folder 12)
      - Reading notes (miscellaneous loose), undated. (Box 32, Folder 13)
      - Reading notes on various works (bound), undated. (Box 32, Folder 14)
      - Reading notes on various works (bound), undated. (Box 32, Folder 15)
      - "Reading, recreation and amusements for the insane" (report to the Association of Medical Superintendents of American Institutions for the Insane), 1848; undated. (Box 32, Folder 16)
      - "References for pamphlet," undated. (Box 32, Folder 17)
      - "Religious observations" (essay/report), undated. (Box 32, Folder 18)
      - "Remarks respecting a proposed law prohibiting the Western Asylum from making selection as to cases applying for admission to that institution," undated. (Box 32, Folder 19)
      - "Reports of American asylums for the insane," 1851. (Box 32, Folder 20)
      - Responsibility for patients who leave the asylum, Notice regarding, 1855. (Box 32, Folder 21)
      - Salaries, Notes on, undated. (Box 32, Folder 22)
      - Salaries of officers, List of, 1856. (Box 32, Folder 23)
      - Selection of sites for insane asylums (essay), undated. (Box 32, Folder 24)
      - "Sermons of Capt. James DeCocy (copied by Edward Petticolas) and "Epistles of Capt. James Cossy," 1853; undated. (Box 32, Folder 25)
      - Servants for hire, Notice to those with, undated. (Box 32, Folder 26)
      - Servants offered for hire, Lists of, 1846; 1851. (Box 32, Folder 27)
      - Sewerage, Contract for construction of, undated. (Box 32, Folder 28)
      - "Silver Sutures in Surgery," the Anniversary Discourse before the New York Academy of Medicine, by J. Marion Sims, M.D., 1858. (Box 32, Folder 29)
      - Slave patients, Notice regarding, undated. (Box 32, Folder 30)
      - Slaves, List of (with age and race), undated. (Box 32, Folder 31)
      - Southern Protection Insurance Company, Advertisement for, undated. (Box 32, Folder 32)
      - "Special report concerning repairs and improvements," undated. (Box 32, Folder 33)
      - "Special report concerning the number of officers, their salaries, etc.," 1856. (Box 32, Folder 34)
      - "Specifications of the proposed addition to the northern building of the Western Asylum" (circular), undated (circa 1848). (Box 32, Folder 35)
      - Statistical information by locality, undated (circa 1840). (Box 32, Folder 36)
      - Store House, Plans and elevations for (photocopies), undated. (Box 32, Folder 37)
      - Superintendent's reports (drafts), 1847-1848. (Box 32, Folder 38)
      - Supplies, Request for prices of, undated. (Box 32, Folder 39)
      - "Supposed causes of insanity" (photocopies), 1847. (Box 32, Folder 40)
      - Sutures, Notes on, undated. (Box 32, Folder 41)
      - "The annexation of Texas" (essay), undated. (Box 32, Folder 42)
      - "The bibliography of insanity" (with notes), undated. (Box 32, Folder 43)
      - "The Eastern Asylum for the maintenance and cure of insane persons" (circular), undated. (Box 32, Folder 44)
      - "The Last Lines of Edgar A. Poe (Annabel Lee)" and "There is Something Good in Every Heart" (poems), undated. (Box 32, Folder 45)
      - The Medical Times and Gazette, Vol. 16, 1858. (Box 32, Folder 46)
      - The Opal, edited by the patients of the State Lunatic Asylum, Utica, NY, 1852 February and June. (Box 32, Folder 47)
      - The Peninsular Journal of Medicine and the Collateral Sciences, Vol. IV, No. V, 1856. (Box 32, Folder 48)
      - "The rate of board in lunatic asylums" (essay), 1853. (Box 32, Folder 49)
      - Transportation of lunatics, Resolution concerning the, 1854. (Box 32, Folder 50)
      - Travel itinerary, 1850. (Box 32, Folder 51)
      - Traveling expenses, Notes on, undated. (Box 32, Folder 52)
      - Treatment, Notes on (miscellaneous topics), undated. (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Treatment history, Male patients (fragment), 1850. (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Treatment registers, 1833-1843. (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Treatment registers, 1844-1845. (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Treatment registers, 1846-1848. (Box 33, Folder 5)
      - Treatment registers, 1849-1850; 1861. (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - Treatment registers (fragments), undated. (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - Vacancy at Williamsburg Female Academy, Notice to teachers regarding a, undated. (Box 33, Folder 8)
      - Ventilation of buildings, Contract for, 1872. (Box 33, Folder 9)
      - Virginia Gazette circular, 1854. (Box 33, Folder 10)
      - Visitor's pass to Eastern Lunatic Asylum, undated. (Box 33, Folder 11)
      - Williamsburg Male Academey and Female Academy, Meeting notices for, 1856-1857. (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - Work done by the Male Department, List of, 1843. (Box 33, Folder 13)
      - Writings of patients, undated. (Box 33, Folder 14)
      - Wrought iron, Statement of purchase, 1842. (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - Ledgers
      - Journal (possibly belonging to Clara Harding?), undated. (Volume 037)
      - Journal (possibly belonging to Thomas M. Spragins?), undated (circa 1852). (Volume 038)
      - Memorandum book [includes draft report, address book for next of kin; and list of patients for whom clothing was written], 1859-1861; 1887. (Volume 039)
- Series V. Financial Registers, 1882-1974., Extent: 51 volumes. (Volume 40-90, 122.)
  Restricted: financial registers containing patient names or information that are less than 125 years old. Some records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served.
  Contains a variety of registers that document the financial history of the hospital. Included are ledgers devoted to particular accounts, such as the building fund, contingent fund and support fund. Also included are check stub books related to the Additions and Improvements Fund and the Auditor of Public Accounts. Other ledgers contain information on contracts awarded, patient personal funds and charges, steward's sales, transportation and amusement. The largest subset of financial registers are the general ledgers and general journals. The general ledgers served as the final accounting of funds received and disbursed. The ledgers provide information on money spent for capital outlay projects, legal expenses, medical supplies, food, amusement, equipment, postage, telephone and telegrams. Ledgers for more recent years include information on grant monies, accounts such as the John D. Rockefeller Jr. Donation Fund and the Chapel Buildings Fund, and appropriations for the Behavior Modification Program. In most cases, each general ledger is accompanied by a journal that features more descriptive information about accounts paid and received. Researchers should not that the dates on the ledgers and journal often overlap for unknown reasons. Several of the later general journals are restricted due to the presence of patient names and Medicaid information.
  Arranged alphabetically by the title of the register.
  - Account book, 1935-1939. (Volume 040)
  - Account book, 1953-1957. (Volume 041)
  - Bills received, Account of, 1907-1919. (Volume 042)
  - Building Fund, Accounts of the, 1885-1901. (Volume 043)
  - Cash book, 1911-1920. (Volume 044)
  - Cash book, Contingent Fund, 1903-1928. (Volume 045)
  - Cash book, Disbursements, 1923-1930. (Volume 046)
  - Check stub book, Additions and Improvements Fund, 1910-1911. (Volume 047)
  - Check stub book, Additions and Improvements Fund (infirmary employees?), 1914-1915. (Volume 048)
  - Check stub book, Auditor of Public Accounts, 1902-1912. (Volume 049)
  - Contracts, Register of, 1909-1921. (Volume 050)
  - Contracts for supplies, Award of, 1906-1924. (Volume 051)
  - Current accounts, Index to, 1887-1888. (Volume 052)
  - General journal, 1923-1927. (Volume 053)
  - General journal, 1947-1949. (Volume 054)
  - General journal, 1969-1970. (Volume 055)
  - General journal, 1970-1971. (Volume 056)
  - General journal, 1971-1972. (Volume 057)
  - General journal, 1972-1973. (Volume 058)
  - General journal, 1973-1974. (Volume 059)
  - General ledger, 1916-1927. (Volume 060)
  - General ledger, 1923-1927. (Volume 061)
  - General ledger, 1923-1929. (Volume 062)
  - General ledger, 1929-1934. (Volume 063)
  - General ledger, 1932-1938. (Volume 064)
  - General ledger, 1934-1939. (Volume 065)
  - General ledger, 1938-1939. (Volume 066)
  - General ledger, 1941-1944. (Volume 067)
  - General ledger, 1947-1949. (Volume 068)
  - General ledger, 1951-1952. (Volume 069)
  - General ledger, 1970-1971. (Volume 070)
  - General ledger, 1971-1972. (Volume 071)
  - General ledger, 1973-1974. (Volume 072)
  - Insurance expirations, Register of, 1923-1944. (Volume 073)
  - Invoice book / Day book, 1882-1885. (Volume 074)
  - Patient account book, 1935-1939. (Volume 075)
  - Patients' private funds, Account of, 1898-1911. (Volume 076)
  - Patients' private funds, Account of, 1901-1907. (Volume 077)
  - Patients' private funds, Account of, 1902-1909. (Volume 078)
  - Patients' private funds, Disbursements, 1911-1924. (Volume 079)
  - Patients' private funds, Disbursements, 1924-1931. (Volume 080)
  - Patients' private funds, Receipts and disbursements, 1931-1934. (Volume 081)
  - Pay patient funds, Account of, 1884-1928. (Volume 082)
  - Pay patients, Account of, 1884-1917. (Volume 083)
  - Pay patients, Journal of charges, 1937-1939. (Volume 084)
  - Pay patients and bonds, Account of, 1866-1869 (found in a volume of Building Committee minutes). (Volume 122)
  - Steward's sales, Journal of, 1923-1934. (Volume 085)
  - Support Fund, Account of the, 1903-1907. (Volume 086)
  - Transportation register / Amusement Fund account book, 1905-1934. (Volume 087)
  - Trial balance account book, 1923-1934. (Volume 088)
  - Trial balance account book, 1934-1939. (Volume 089)
  - Voucher register, 1934-1939. (Volume 090)
- Series VI. History Files, 1942-1999., Extent: .75 cu. ft. (Box 34-35.)
  Contains files related to histories written about Eastern State Hospital, the Galt family and other mental health topics. Included is a card catalog of books once held in the Galt book collection, articles about the hospital, written histories and supporting documentation.
  - "Archival Treasures from the E.S.H. Library," undated. (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - Articles, 1942-1986. (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1989-1999. (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Articles, undated. (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Articles and history-related documents, 1953-1996. (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Articles and history-related documents, undated. (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Articles and history-related documents (Patient Librarian), 1959-1995. (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Articles and history-related documents (Patient Librarian), 1959-1995. (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Galt book collection, 1959; undated. (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Galt book collection, Card catalog of (A-C), undated. (Box 34, Folder 10)
  - Galt book collection, Card catalog of (D-L), undated. (Box 34, Folder 11)
  - Galt book collection, Card catalog of (M-P), undated. (Box 34, Folder 12)
  - Galt book collection, Card catalog of (R-W), undated. (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - Galt family histories and information, 1982-1991; undated. (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Histories, Miscellaneous (Eastern State Hospital, Galt, etc.), undated. (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - "Members of the Galt Family Associated with Eastern State Hospital," (list), undated. (Box 35, Folder 2)
  - Rare books (Galt-related) at William and Mary's Swem Library, List of, undated. (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - "Some Historical Notes on John Minson Galt, Jr. and the Civil War at Eastern State Hospital," undated. (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - "The story of Eastern State Hospital, 1766-1953," undated. (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Transorbital lobotomy, History of, 1996. (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Treatment, History of, undated. (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Written histories and related material, circa 1948-1995. (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Written histories and related material, undated. (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Written histories and related material (from Charles M. Hunter), 1957-1996. (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Written histories and related material (Medical Records Supervisor), circa 1950-1969. (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Written histories and related material (Medical Records Supervisor), circa 1950-1959. (Box 35, Folder 12)
- Series VII. Inventory and Supply Registers, 1876-1976., Extent: 30 volumes. (Volume 92-121.)
  Contains a variety of registers related to the inventorying and issuing of food and other items at the hospital, such as day books, registers of stores issued and received, requisition and invoice registers, and a farm production register.
  The day books describe supplies maintained by and issued to particular staff members or units such as the matron, supervisor, chief cook, steward, and drug room or for particular purposes such as housekeeping. Examples of items inventoried include whiskey and wine, various foodstuffs, clothing, toiletries, and tobacco. Handwritten notations made by the matron or supervisor can be found in some of the earlier daybooks.
  The registers of stores issued contain lists of particular supplies, food and other items that were issued to various staff or hospital units. These supplies include wagons, utensils, clothing, bedding, personal care items, and food. The registers of stores received account for the receipt of the above items before they were used or distributed to patients and staff.
  A register of farm production, as well as registers of requisitions and invoices can also be found in this series. The farm production register contains an inventory of fruits, vegetables and meat raised and harvested by the hospital. The requisition and invoice registers contain additional information about supplies bought by the hospital.
  - Central supply record book, 1962-1964. (Volume 092)
  - Day Book, 1882-1883. (Volume 093)
  - Day Book, 1884-1886. (Volume 094)
  - Day Book, 1885-1887. (Volume 095)
  - Day Book, 1888-1890. (Volume 096)
  - Day Book (Daily Issues), 1892-1894. (Volume 097)
  - Day Book (Daily Issues), 1895-1897. (Volume 098)
  - Day Book (Daily Issues), 1897-1899. (Volume 099)
  - Day Book (Daily Issues), 1899-1900. (Volume 100)
  - Day Book (Daily Issues), 1901-1902. (Volume 101)
  - Day Book, 1902-1905. (Volume 102)
  - Day Book, 1905-1907. (Volume 103)
  - Day Book, 1907-1909. (Volume 104)
  - Day Book, 1909-1911. (Volume 105)
  - Farm Products, Register of, 1916-1924. (Volume 106)
  - Invoices, Register of, 1882-1886. (Volume 107)
  - Items loaned and/or borrowed, Register of, 1967-1976. (Volume 108)
  - Requisitions, Register of, 1876-1878. (Volume 109)
  - Requisitions (Invoices), Register of, 1883-1885. (Volume 110)
  - Store Invoices Received, Register of, 1895-1900. (Volume 111)
  - Stores (Classified Receipts), Account of, 1876-1890. (Volume 112)
  - Stores Issued, Classified Account of, 1876-1882. (Volume 113)
  - Stores Issued (Miscellaneous and Subsistence), Register of, 1882-1885. (Volume 114)
  - Stores Issued (Miscellaneous and Subsistence), Register of, 1886-1889. (Volume 115)
  - Stores Issued (Miscellaneous and Subsistence), Register of, 1889-1892. (Volume 116)
  - Stores Issued, Register of, 1899-1907. (Volume 117)
  - Stores Issued, Register of, 1907-1908. (Volume 118)
  - Stores Received (Miscellaneous and Subsistence), Register of, 1890-1892. (Volume 119)
  - Stores Received, Register of, 1899-1907. (Volume 120)
  - Stores Received, Register of, 1907-1908. (Volume 121)
- Series VIII. Minutes, 1770-1989., Extent: .675 cu. ft.; 27 volumes. (Box 36-37;, Volume 122-147.)
  Contains the minutes of the Court/Board of Directors and the Executive Committee, as well as minutes of the Board of Physicians and Building Committee. The majority of the volumes contain minutes of the Court/Board of Directors. The history of the Board begins with the Court of Directors which was the original advisory committee that closely supervised the operation of the asylum. The Court of Directors was later renamed the Board of Directors, and its nine appointed members were required to meet on a quarterly basis. In 1903, the Board of Directors was replaced by a three-person group called the Special Board of Directors. There may be some overlapping use of older and newer names, but they describe the same basic administrative body. The first volume of minutes contains a deed for the land on which the original hospital sat, the articles of agreement, and description of the area and original buildings. In some cases, the minute books have overlapping dates, due to the presence of "rough minutes" in addition to the official minutes of Board meetings.
  Also related to the Board minutes are the minutes of the Executive Committee. The Executive Committee was composed of a small number of members of the Court of Directors/Board of Directors. The Executive Committee was responsible for reviewing the superintendent's reports, auditing the steward's monthly expense accounts, and overseeing other matters that arose between Board meetings. An index to the Executive Committee minutes exists for the years 1901-1913.
  Additionally, this series contains the minutes of the Board of Physicians, which include patient and treatment information, as well as discussion of hospital business and operations. Also included are the minutes of the Building Committee (or Committee on Construction), which include records of money spent on construction projects, buildings, grounds and the general maintenance of the hospital structures. Also included here are several folders of minutes from the Local Building Committee, which was responsible for managing construction projects at Eastern State.
  Arranged alphabetically by board or committee and then chronologically within.
  - Building Committee, 1871-1886 (also contains Pay patients and bonds, Account of, 1866-1869). (Volume 122)
  - Directors, Court of, (copy one), 1770-1801. [Originals - Do not serve] (Volume 123)
  - Directors, Court of, (copy two), 1770-1801. (Volume 124)
  - Directors, Court of, (copy three), 1770-1801. (Volume 125)
  - Directors, Court of, 1822-1842. (Volume 126)
  - Directors, Court of, 1833-1843. (Volume 127)
  - Directors, Court of, 1843-1849. (Volume 128)
  - Directors, Court of, 1849-1853. (Volume 129)
  - Directors, Court of / Directors, Board of, 1851-1854 (also contains Patient admissions and discharges, Register of, 1868-1869). (Volume 130)
  - Directors, Board of, 1853-1857. (Volume 131)
  - Directors, Board of, 1858-1866. (Volume 132)
  - Directors, Board of, 1866-1869. (Volume 133)
  - Directors, Board of, 1869-1875. (Volume 134)
  - Directors, Board of, 1875-1887. (Volume 135)
  - Directors, Board of, 1887-1896. (Volume 136)
  - Directors, Board of, 1896-1903. (Volume 137)
  - Directors, Board of, 1902-1914. (Volume 138)
  - Directors, Special Board of, 1912-1914. (Volume 138)
  - Directors, Special Board of, 1913-1932. (Volume 139)
  - Director's meetings, 1976-1977. (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee, 1868-1882. (Volume 140)
  - Executive Committee, 1869-1871. (Volume 141)
  - Executive Committee, 1872-1875. (Volume 142)
  - Executive Committee, 1875-1887. (Volume 143)
  - Executive Committee, 1887-1901. (Volume 144)
  - Executive Committee / Directors, Special Board of, 1901-1913. (Volume 145)
  - Executive Committee Book, Index to, 1901-1913. (Volume 146)
  - Local Building Committee, 1944. (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Local Building Committee, 1945. (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - Local Building Committee, 1946. (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Local Building Committee, 1947; undated. (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Local Building Committee, 1948 July-August. (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Local Building Committee, 1948 September. (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Local Building Committee, 1948 October-December. (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Local Building Committee, 1949 January-March. (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - Local Building Committee, 1949 May-June. (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - Local Building Committee, 1949 July-December. (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Local Building Committee, 1950 January-March. (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Local Building Committee, 1950 May-September. (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Local Building Committee, 1950 October-December. (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - Local Building Committee, 1951 January-April. (Box 36, Folder 15)
  - Local Building Committee, 1951 May-December. (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Local Building Committee, 1952 January-June. (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Local Building Committee, 1956 July-October. (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Local Building Committee, 1956 November-December. (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Local Building Committee, 1957 January-February. (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Local Building Committee, 1957 March-May. (Box 37, Folder 6)
  - Local Building Committee, 1957 June-August. (Box 37, Folder 7)
  - Local Building Committee, 1957 September-December. (Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Physicians, Board of, 1886-1903. (Volume 147)
  - Quality Assurance Steering Committee, 1988-1989. (Box 37, Folder 9)
  - State Hospital Board, 1948. (Box 37, Folder 10)
  - Superintendent's meeting (to adopt building standards), 1945. (Box 37, Folder 11)
- Series IX. News Clippings and Summaries, 1964-2008., Extent: 4.275 cu. ft. (Box 38-47.)
  Contains two categories of press material: newspaper clippings and news summaries. Some overlap exists between the two groups. The news clippings were collected and maintained by Eastern State Hospital staff and are mainly photocopies from local newspapers of articles about Eastern State Hospital and mental health topics generally. Several folders of prominent articles are labeled by title and arranged at the end of the clippings section. The news summaries are booklets of photocopied articles compiled by the Legislation and Public Relations Office of the Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services for submission to the Secretary of Health and Human Resources. The articles included in the summaries range from general health topics to specific stories about the state hospitals.
  Arranged by type of record and then chronologically within.
  - News Clippings
    - 1970-1973. (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - 1974. (Box 38, Folder 2)
    - 1975-1976. (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - 1977-1978. (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - 1979. (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - 1979. (Box 38, Folder 6)
    - 1979. (Box 38, Folder 7)
    - 1979. (Box 38, Folder 8)
    - 1979. (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - undated (circa 1970-1979). (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - 1980. (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - 1980. (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - 1980. (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - 1981. (Box 38, Folder 14)
    - 1981. (Box 39, Folder 1)
    - 1981. (Box 39, Folder 2)
    - 1982. (Box 39, Folder 3)
    - 1982. (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - 1983. (Box 39, Folder 5)
    - 1984. (Box 39, Folder 6)
    - 1984. (Box 39, Folder 7)
    - 1985. (Box 39, Folder 8)
    - 1985. (Box 39, Folder 9)
    - 1986. (Box 40, Folder 1)